Guide to the Ethiopia Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ethiopia collection
1867-2013
MS 1516
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.76
(13 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, journals, printed material, ephemera, and photographs relating to the history of Ethiopia and the current political and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, journals, printed material, ephemera, and photographs relating to the history of Ethiopia and the current political and social conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Italo-Ethiopian War, 1935-1936; Jews, Ethiopian; Oromo (African people); Tigrinya (African people); Ethiopia -- Description and travel; Ethiopia -- Foreign relations -- Italy; Ethiopia -- History -- 1490-1889; Ethiopia -- History -- 1889-1974; Ethiopia -- Politics and government; Ethiopia -- Social conditions; Italy -- Foreign relations -- Ethiopia; Photographs -- Ethiopia; Ethiopian Peoples' Revolutionary Party; Relief Society of Tigray; Abyssinian Expedition ( 1867-1868)
- Inventory
  - Italo-Abyssinian dispute: books; journals; letters; photographs, 1868-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ethiopian liberation and relief: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1964-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1967-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Falasha Jews: newspaper clippings; printed material, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oromo liberation: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1981-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tigray liberation: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1981-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Political organizations: printed material, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ministry of Information Press Department: printed material, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Government documents: journals; reports, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Massawa and Asmara: photograph album, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Photographs of Ethiopia 1958-1982 by Shemelis Desta": exhibition in the West Midlands, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Events in Dar es Salaam": photograph album by E. Gladden, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Tour to Gibraltar and Tangier": photograph album by E. Gladden, 1968 May-June (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs. See also: Kenya Collection, Manuscript Group Number 1523 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-144
  - Additional printed materials and photographs, 1936-1941, 1958, 1977-1978, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-018
  - Additional printed materials, 1936, 1975-1985, 1994, 1997 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-036
  - "Forward" [newsletter of the World Wide Federation of Ethiopian Students], 1976 Dec, 1977 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - REST Bulletin [Relief Society of Tigray, Ethiopian Human Rights Council report], 1988, 1994, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Storm: Somali, Tigray & Oromo Resistance Monitor" [newsletter], 1981 Jun, 1982 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Struggle" [journal of the Worldwide Federation of Ethiopian Students], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Tigray" [newsletter of The Union of Tigreans in North America], [198-?] February 18, 1981 Nov, 1982 Dec, 1986 Jan (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tigray People's Liberation Front [news release], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials [human rights, art, archeology], 1962, 1965, 1983, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photograph album [Italian, over 350 photographs of people, animals, and scenery in Ethiopia; a few Suez Canal and military shots], [193-] (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-040
  - Collector cards representing Ethiopian flags, coins, medals, monuments, and individuals, Rastafarian badge, 1928, 1936, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - La Lune, editorial cartoon, "Theodoros, Roi d'Abyssinie, le Lion d'Abyssinie et le Lion Britannique", 1867 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Relief Society of Tigray (REST) UK Support Committee, newsletter, press release, locust update, appeal letter, 1987 April-May, September 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American-African Affairs, vol. 10, no. 6, 1976 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1920-1990, undated; Accession 2011-M-005
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged as received.
  - Publications
    - Berhanena Selam (2), Circa 1920 - 1930s (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      The leading Ethiopian newspaper of the 1920s and 1930s, possibly commemorative issues for the coronation of Haile Selassie. The text is in Amharic.
    - Hurggie Dima: The struggle in Tokkumma Oromo Organization in N. America (TOONA), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Oroma Speaks: A publication of the Oromo Liberation Front, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Relief Society of Tigray: Annual Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sagalee Waldhaansso, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Seventh Report on the Drought and Overall Food Supply in Ethiopia, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Waldhaanss o: Journal of the Union of Oromo Students in North America, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Maps
    - Felt maps (3) of Ethiopia, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      The back of each map reads "From Tiringo Tulu to Zerihun H/G." A brass cross adorns the front of each map.
  - Photographs
    - Color photographs (9) of historic Coptic Christian churches and sites in Ethiopia, including among others, Lalibela (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Additional material, 1920-2013; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1920-2013 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Marshall Graziani documents from shortly after conquest of Ethiopia, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Propaganda art piece in relief of airplane dropping sewing machine by parachute to native, Circa 1939 (Box 2)
  - Posters, Circa 2000s (Folder 3)
    General
    Includes African Union posters.